<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the innocency of the lives, practice, and doctrine of the English preists [sic], Jesuits, and papists relating to the crimes of murther and treason, vnjustly charged on them by E.C. in his narrative wherein are discouered his grosse mistakes, his wilfull falsifications, his shamefull falshoodes, and his groundlesse vniust accusations of the English papists.</title>
            <author>Warner, John, 1628-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W908A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221952</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833196</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833196</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37671</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67646)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37671)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2161:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the innocency of the lives, practice, and doctrine of the English preists [sic], Jesuits, and papists relating to the crimes of murther and treason, vnjustly charged on them by E.C. in his narrative wherein are discouered his grosse mistakes, his wilfull falsifications, his shamefull falshoodes, and his groundlesse vniust accusations of the English papists.</title>
                  <author>Warner, John, 1628-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Antwerp? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Permissu superiorum. 1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Warner.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Durham University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37671:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37671:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE of the Innocency of the LIVES, PRACTICE, AND DOCTRINE of the ENGLISH PREISTS, JESUITS, and PAPISTS. relating to the Crimes of MVRTHER and TREASON, vnjuſtly charged on them by E. C. in his NARRATIVE</p>
            <p>Wherein are diſcouered
<list>
                  <item>His Groſſe Miſtakes,</item>
                  <item>His wilfull Falſifications,</item>
                  <item>His shamefull Falshoodes, and</item>
                  <item>His groundleſſe vniuſt Accuſations</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>OF THE ENGLISH PAPISTS.</p>
            <p>
               <q>In malâ Causâ non poſsunt alìter: ſed quis coegit eos malam cauſam habere? <bibl>Aguſt.</bibl> A bad cauſe, <hi>(ſuch is the charging Innocent Perſons with greivous crimes)</hi> cannot be better managed: But what forced them to vndertake ſuch a bad cauſe?</q>
            </p>
            <p>ANSWER: <q>Odio habuerunt me gratis. <bibl>Joan. 15.25.</bibl> They hate the <hi>Myſtical Body</hi> of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> without any cauſe at all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:37671:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37671:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Narrative,</hi> which I here examin in its deſign is like the reſt of the Libells, which haue of late appeared with that title, but is far different in the meanes it makes vſe of, to compaſſe it. All conſpire to perſwade the world, that <hi>Catholicks are not fit to be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted in any Government,</hi> by reaſon of the Deſigns contrary to them, which we drive on. But the firſt <hi>Narratives</hi> differre from this, that thoſe alleadged ſeveral pretended <hi>Treaſons</hi> of <hi>Papiſts</hi> them aliue, either committed, or deſigned in our days, in the preſence of thoſe <hi>Informers,</hi> and which might haue ruined Church, and ſtate had they not been prevented by the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable diſcouery of thoſe villanies: ſo they were made vp of perſonall Acts either done, or deſigned, as was pretended, by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> then aliue: and which therefore were iuſtly charged on them, if the Informations were tru. But that plea being euidently baffled by the many contradictions, and improbabilities it contained, this <hi>Narratiue</hi> arraignes the <hi>English Catholicks</hi> in another way, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them with what its Authour thought blame-worthy in any Profeſſor of the ſame <hi>Religion,</hi> how diſtant ſoever he was from <hi>English Catholicks,</hi> both in place where, and time when he lived. To this intent he takes the Liberty to range ouer all ages, and Countries, where <hi>Catholick Religion</hi> hath been profeſt; and if in this, or any former age, in <hi>Spaine,</hi> or <hi>Italy, France, Portugal,</hi> or <hi>Germany</hi> he finds an indiſcreet Schooleman, a Cholerick Pope, or a Paſſionat Prince, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, Speake, or Act reprehenſibly, all that is charged vpon the <hi>English Catholiks</hi> in this Libel. So what the D. de <hi>Alva</hi> did in the Low-countries, what <hi>Lewis</hi> VIII. in <hi>Languedoc,</hi> and what <hi>S. Gregory</hi> the greate writ aboue a thouſand yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res agoe to <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour, all theſe, I ſay, and many more ſerue to increaſe the indightment drawn vp againſt vs in this wiſe <hi>Narratiue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we ſee this our Freind hath opened a way to find matter enough to charge vs with. But with what colour of Iuſtice can any of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe illegall actions (ſuppoſe them ſuch) be charged on vs, who haue no more hand in them, then in the Actions of the <hi>Cham of Tartary,</hi> or the <hi>Greate Mogul,</hi> or thoſe of <hi>Marius,</hi> and <hi>Sylla,</hi> ſeing theſe were dead befor we were borne, ſo was <hi>Lewis</hi> VIII.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37671:3"/>and <hi>S. Gregory;</hi> and with the D. de <hi>Alua</hi> we had no more communication, then with the great <hi>Mogul,</hi> or the <hi>Cham</hi> With what Topicke then can <hi>we be made</hi> anſwearable for thoſe faults, of which we knew nothing, vnleſſe this worthy perſon thinks, we could know, before we had any Being</p>
            <p>What Innocency can be proof, when it comes to be tryed as ours is? We were firſt charged with perſonall Actions, as actually and perſonnally plotting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſacred Majeſties life and government. The falſity of this charge being made euident, whereas we ſhould be acquitted, a new endightment is drawn vp againſt vs by E. C. containing all the faults, he had read, or feigned of the Catholicks of what ſoeuer country, or age: all which he hath depoſed in this <hi>Naratiue.</hi> Why ſo? he conſiders all <hi>Catholicks</hi> that are, or haue been, as one Maſſe of perdition, one Reprobate Perſon, whereof each part is made anſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reable for the bad Actions of the whole, and of each other part of it.</p>
            <p>How hard ſoeuer it be for any Innocency to ſtand ſuch afiery Ordeale, yet ours hath ſtood this, and either the vertu of paſt and foreign <hi>Papiſts</hi> hath been ſo wonderfull, or his Blindneſſe ſo greate, that all which Hyſtories of paſt times, or remote partes afforded him, could not ſatisfy his hatred of vs, nor compleate his charge againſt vs, without helping it out, with new crimes of his owne feighning. Witneſſe what he cites page 6. out of <hi>Suarez,</hi> that <hi>it is lawfull for any man to kill an excommunicated King.</hi> Which he relates as <hi>Suarez</hi> his Doctrine: whereas in <hi>Suarez</hi> after thoſe words, immediatly follows this cenſure vpon them: <hi>This poſition is moſt falſe. Haec Propoſitio falſiſsima eſt.</hi> You ſee <hi>Suarez</hi> doth abſolutely condemn that very Doctrine, which he is accuſed to haue taught.</p>
            <p>Againe page 9. he aſſures, that <hi>none but monyed men can get abſolution from their fins in the Roman Church. Peccatorum venia non niſi nummatis impenditur.</hi> A thing ſo falſe, that I defie any man liuing to produce one ſingle inſtance of a man, who vpon ſcore of Poverty was refuſed abſolution. And in all our Churches our Confeſſion ſeats are as free and open to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> as to <hi>Craeſus.</hi> More examples of the ſincerity of this <hi>tale teller</hi> wil occurre in the following Treatiſe. Theſe two will ſuffice for a ſhew of his Art.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Recrimination</hi> is a familiar, ordinary, and obuious <hi>Apology:</hi> yet I think it the leaſt ſatisfactory, &amp; worſt of all as being fitter to multiply the number of guilty Perſons, then proue the Innocency of any one. For it doth not follow, that M. Whitebreade was Innocent, if it ſhould be proued, that <hi>Oates</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had an averſion to the Royal family. Or that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are loyal ſubjects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Wicleffiſts</hi> held ſeditious Doctrines. Yet I haue been perſwaded not to omit that way of anſwering too, to obliege the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> if poſſible, to combat wicked maximes in their own, as well as in <hi>Papiſts,</hi> &amp; to moue them to ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37671:3"/>of humane frailties, to which they are much more ſubject then we. For two very material differences are obſervable betwixt the things they charge <hi>Papiſts</hi> with, &amp; what the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are accuſed off.</p>
            <p>The firſt: that thoſe charged on vs are conſiſtant with Authority. For what bad effect could thoſe words of a Pope Spoken in paſſion haue: <hi>Either I will haue Philips Crown, or he shall haue my Myter?</hi> They forewarned the King of the danger, by diſcouering ſuch a bad talent in the Pope againſt him. And moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer probably the Pope himſelf hauing ſlept vpon it, was aſhamed of ſuch a paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate expreſſion ſo vnbeſeeming his Dignity. Whereas the Doctrines we charge on <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> are ſetled ſeditious maximes, which lay the Axe at the roote of all Authority Ciuil, and Eccleſiaſtical. For example that of the <hi>Wicleffiſts; no man in ſtate of mortal ſin retaines any Authority.</hi> What King can be ſure of his crown, what Biſhop of his myter where this Doctrine prevailes.</p>
            <p>Another difference is, that we haue long ſince rejected theſe Doctrines (if there were euer any ſuch amongſt vs) and I challenge Proteſtants to ſhew any <hi>Papiſt</hi> aliue, who doth teach them. Whereas the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> retaine the ſame vnretracted, vncondemned to this moment, &amp; vpon occaſions ſpread them a new As that ſeditious maxime of the <hi>Wicleffiſts,</hi> (of which I haue ſpoken.) which <hi>Oates</hi> hath printed in the Dedicatory of his <hi>Narratiue</hi> to the King himſelf. Whence followes a</p>
            <p>Third difference: that what is found blame worthy in our Predeceſſors cannot be layd to our charge, ſeing we neither practice, nor teach it; nay our Prelates haue condemned it, as we ſhall ſee at the end of this Preface; whereas <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are anſwerable for the doctrines of their Fore fathers, and all the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious conſequences flowing from them, becauſe they neuer condemned, or diſowned them; but do ſtill approue of them.</p>
            <p>Wherfore ſeing nothing can be with luſtice charged on <hi>English Catholicks,</hi> for whom alone I plead: ſeing their life is ſo clear from ſin, &amp; their Doctrine from errour, that neither can be blamed without a calumny, nor our reputation wounded but through the ſide of Truth: Let <hi>Oates</hi> &amp; <hi>Prance, Euerard</hi> &amp; <hi>Dugdale, Smith,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieniſon, Bolron, dangerfeild,</hi> &amp; E. C. (one for any thing I know like the reſt) multiply their <hi>Narratiues</hi> as often as they pleaſe, &amp; ſtuffe them with ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies to as great a bulke, as their little wit, &amp; great malice will p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmit, the only effect of thoſe Libels will be to cloud our Reputation from the eyes of the people for a time, &amp; giue them ſome bad impreſſions of vs: yet our Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency will diſperſe thoſe miſts, &amp; ſhine ſo brightly, as to be conſpicuous to the whole world. And the People it ſelf whome their Miniſters ſeduce with theſe Fables, &amp; diſingenious Arts, will giue to vs, &amp; to the Libellers their due; to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37671:4"/>vs, in acquitting vs of the crimes charged vniuſtly vpon vs; &amp; to them, by fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them guilty of vncharitable lies, at the priuate tribunal of each ones Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>It is vncertaine when we may expect to ſee an end of theſe diſputes betwixt our <hi>Innocency,</hi> and their <hi>malice.</hi> Nothing put a ſtop to the falſe accuſations of the Authour of the firſt &amp; greateſt <hi>Narratiue,</hi> but his loſſe of credit, by the open diſcovery of his lies. A like loſſe of credit may happily put aſtop to the pens of theſe Libellers. And I doubt not, but the better part of our nation will be glad to ſee <hi>Truth</hi> aſſerted againſt <hi>Falshood,</hi> &amp; <hi>Innocency</hi> triumphing ouer <hi>Malicious ſlaunders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the Authour of this <hi>Narratiue</hi> I will only lay, that if he had not Honeſty to ſpeake only the truth, he had wit enough to conceale his name, that he might preſerve his credit, notwithſtanding all his lies.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe I ſhall haue occaſion to cite in our Defence hereafter ſome Decrees of Popes (to which all <hi>Catholiks</hi> ſubmit) in our vindication, I will here giue an extract of ſuch Propoſitions condemned in them which relate to MURTHER, &amp; equivocation.</p>
            <div type="document">
               <head>Out of the Decree of Allexandre VII. Anno 1665. 24. Septembris.</head>
               <p>On that day, 28. propoſitions were condemned vnder paine of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication reſerued to his Holineſs, vpon any that ſhould practice, teach, or hold lawfull any of them, or ſpeake of them otherwiſe, then condemning, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning them.</p>
               <p>Amongſt theſe the ſeventeenth is as follows:</p>
               <q rend="italic">
                  <p n="17">17. Eſt licitum Religioſo, vel Clerico Calumniatorem grauia crimina de ſe, vel de ſuâ Religione ſpargere minantem occidere, quando alius modus defendendi non ſuppetit: vti ſuppetere non videtur, ſi calumniator ſit paratus vel ipſi Religioſo, vel ejus Religioni publicè, &amp; coram grauiſtimis viris praedicta impingere niſi occidatur.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. Licet interficere falſum Accuſatorem, falſos teſtes, ac etiam judicem, à quo iniqua <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ertò imminet ſententia, ſi alia viâ non poteſt Innocens damnum euitare.</p>
               </q>
               <p>In Engliſh thus:</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>17. Jt is lawfull for a Religious man, or Clergy man, to to kill a Calumniator, who threatens to accuſe him, or his order of ſome greiuous crimes, in caſe there be no other meanes to defend himſelf; &amp; there ſeemes to be no other meanes, when the Sycophant is ready to accuſe him before Perſons of quality, if he be not killed out of hand.</p>
                  <p>18. Jt is lawfull to kill a falſe Accuſer, falſe witneſſes, &amp; euen the Judge, by whome certainly the Accuſed ſhall ſhortly be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if the Jnnocent can by no other meanes avoyde the dammage.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37671:4"/>
               <head>Out of the Decree of JNNOCENT XI. publiſht 2. March 1679. ſtilo no.</head>
               <p>On that day Sixty fiue Propoſitions were condemned, &amp; in alike manner for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden vnder paine of Excommunication. Here I giue thoſe, which I ſhall cite hereafter.</p>
               <q rend="italic">
                  <p n="26">26. Si quis vel ſolus vel coram alijs, ſiue interrogatus, ſiue propriâ ſponte, ſiue recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis causâ, ſiue quocunque alio fine juret, ſe non feciſse aliquid, quod reuerâ fecit, intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo intra ſe aliquid aliud, quod non fecit, vel aliam diem ab eâ, in quâ fecit, vel quodvis aliud additum verum, reuerâ non mentitur, nec eſt periurus.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. Cauſa juſta vtendi his amphibologijs eſt, quoties id neceſſarium, aut vtile eſt ad ſalutem corporis, honorem, res familitares tuendas, vel ad quemlibet alium virtutis actum, ita vt veritatis occultatio cenſeatur tunc expediens, &amp; ſtudioſa,</p>
                  <p n="30">30. Fas eſt viro honorato occidere invaſorem, qui nititur calumniam inferre, ſi aliter haec ignominia vitari nequit: jd m quoque direndum, ſi quis impingat alapam, vel fuſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutiat, &amp; poſt impactam alapam vel ictum fuſtis fugiat.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. Regulariter occidere poſſum furem pro conſervatione vnius aurei.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Jn Engliſh thus.</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>26. Jf any man either alone, or in preſence of others, either vpon examination, or of this own accord, or for diuertiſſement, or for any other intent, ſweares he did not do, what he really did, imagining he did ſome other thing, or ſome other day then he did it on, or any other truth, that man doth neither lye, nor is periured.</p>
                  <p>27. A iuſt cauſe to vſe Equivocation, is when it is neceſſary, or vſefull to preſerve our Health, our Honour, or our goods, or for any other Act of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu; ſoe that when theſe occurre, it may be thought expedient, &amp; laudable to conceale the Truth</p>
                  <p>30. Jt is lawfull for a man of Honour, to kill an aggreſſor, who endeauours to ſlaunder him, if he cannot ſome other way auoyde the diſgrace. The ſame is to be ſayd, if the aggreſſor giue him a box oth'eart, or cudgel him, &amp; having done ſo, runs away.</p>
                  <p>31. I may ordinarily kill a man, to preſence the value of a crowne.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Theſe propoſitions concerning <hi>Equiuocation,</hi> &amp; <hi>Murther,</hi> are in alike manner, condemned, &amp; the greateſt Eccleſiaſticall Cenſure annext to thoſe who teach, practice, or defend any one of them, as probable. And there is no <hi>English Catholick,</hi> Jeſuit, or other, who doth not ſubmit to this Decree.</p>
               <p>As all <hi>English Catholicks,</hi> particularly <hi>Ieſuits</hi> are ready to declare publickly when it ſhall be legally or by Publicke Authority required of them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37671:5"/>
               <head>CHAPTER I. Reflections on the Preface. Where of the pretended danger hanging over libellers againſt Catholicks.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E C: Being very ſenſible how much this ſmall treatiſe will expoſe me to the induſtrious malice, &amp; hatred of all ſtiff, &amp; poſitiue <hi>Papiſts</hi> 
                     <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> My cheife buſineſſe was to find out one, that would boldly ſtand vp with me in the ſame defence, and be ready to iuſtify the truth &amp; honeſt ſincerity of theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſheetes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer: Jt is a common Topick for all who accuſe <hi>Catholecks,</hi> to encreaſe the Odium againſt them, &amp; recommend their own zeale for the common good to the Publicke benevolence by repreſenting the dangers, they expoſe themſelues to, by diſcouering the <hi>faults,</hi> the <hi>conſpiracies,</hi> the <hi>murthers,</hi> the <hi>Treaſons</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> As if the Protection of the Law, the ſecurity of the publick Peace, the vigilancy of Magiſtrates, &amp; the number of Libelling Miniſters, &amp; factious &amp; malicious ſcriblers, were not a ſufficient Protection againſt a few diſarmed men, &amp; for the moſt part Priſoners; but either by Authority a gard muſt be appointed for euery libeller, or elſe by their whining complaints of imaginary dangers, they would engage others without Authority in any illegal Aſſociation for mutuall defence. I leaue to our venerable Iudges to declare whither this ſtand with the law: and his Majeſty's moſt honourable priuy Council to conſider whither it do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the Publicke Peace.</p>
               <p>Whence this Panick Feare, of an inconſiderable number of men, all diſarmed, &amp; moſt of them ether impriſoned, or baniſht? From a bad conſcience, which in the midſt of Peace, &amp; the greateſt ſecurity always thinks of dangers. <hi>Cum Pax ſit, ipſe ſemper inſidias ſuſpicatur.</hi> Job. 15.21. <hi>And the wicked fly, when no body purſues them.</hi> Prou. 28.1. <hi>This is the miſerable condition of ſinners,</hi> ſays S. Chriſoſt. Hom. 8. ad Pop. Antioch. <hi>They ſuſpect all things, they feare shaddows, they tremble at the leaſt noyſe; no body whiſpers, but they think it is againſt them: no body moues, but they ſurmiſe it is to attack them. Such is the nature of ſin: it diſcouers itsſelf, althô none elſe dreame of it, arraignes the guilty perſon without any other witneſſes, &amp; condemnes him at the Tribunal of his owne conſcience from which ſentence there is no appeale.</hi> Hence he flyes, though no body purſues him, thinking that euery man he ſees or phanſies, is his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37671:5"/>Executioner. Is not this a Picture of theſe Champions of the Proteſtant Church &amp; Accuſers of <hi>Papiſts?</hi> Is not this danger alleadged framed by their owne guilty conſcience, which accuſes, arraignes, judges, &amp; condemnes them, &amp; then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents all men as deſigned to execute the ſentence, as <hi>Cain</hi> ſayd, <hi>all who find me, will kill me?</hi> Gen. 4.14. Yet you offer at a reaſon, &amp; here it is.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. The Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are bloudy ones, &amp; ſuch as are directly contrary to the word of God, &amp; the conſtant ſenſe of the Church of all ages, &amp; if blindly followed, what can we euer expect, but Rebellion, Murther Bloud-ſhed, &amp; all manner of confuſion?</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. It is eaſy to ſay <hi>Our Doctrines are contrary to thoſe of the ancient Church</hi> but impoſſible to proue it, becauſe it is euidently falſe. They are <hi>bloody ones,</hi> ſay you. I know no doctrines defended by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> but thoſe contained in the <hi>Profeſsion of Faith</hi> of <hi>Pius</hi> IIII. ſhew one <hi>bloody doctrine</hi> contained in it, &amp; I will yeild the cauſe. If you can ſhew none there, this Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of yours is a greate ſlaunder. You produce indeed ſome pieces out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Authours, with what ſincerity, we will hereafter ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>min. Now ſuppoſe what you ſay be true, and they really held thoſe Doctrines, why ſhould their ſingular ſentiments be the Doctrine of the Church, when others as learned, &amp; pious as they, ſay the contrary, &amp; the cheife Prelates of the Church condemn thoſe opinions? Is there any law which makes each <hi>English Catholick</hi> anſwerable for euery Action, or writing, or word of euery <hi>Sicilian</hi> &amp; <hi>Spaniard?</hi> Jf not, we may be Innocent, hate Murther, &amp; abhor Treaſon, althô ſome of thoſe ſayd the contrary, if they did ſay ſo. Of which hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. As vncontroulable <hi>Dominion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rule</hi> is the ground, &amp; bottom of all their Deſigns, if euer they come to attaine it, KING, <hi>Lords,</hi> &amp; <hi>Commons,</hi> ſhould be the meaneſt of their <hi>Subjects,</hi> &amp; the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> be as one <hi>general Flame.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. were this ſpoken in a Nation, where <hi>Catholick Religion</hi> were vtterly vnknown, you might hope to frighten People from it: but to ſay it in <hi>England,</hi> where during its preuailing there appeared no ſymptom of ſuch diſmall effects, &amp; to <hi>English,</hi> who, know it ſtill preuailes in their neighbouring countries, without thoſe <hi>miſcheifs,</hi> is impudent. What <hi>Kings</hi> more abſolute in their <hi>Dominions,</hi> then the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian,</hi> &amp; <hi>Catholick</hi> Monarks? what ſubjection are they, and their <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> &amp; <hi>Commons</hi> brought vnder? And as for our own Kings, when were they more honoured and obeyed, and their ſubiects at home by loued by their <hi>Freinds,</hi> &amp; <hi>Allyes,</hi> &amp; feared by their ennemys abroad, then when <hi>Papiſts? Popery</hi> inſtructs all <hi>to giue to God, what is Gods, &amp; to Caeſar, what is his:</hi> It traines vp her children in due obedience to <hi>ſpirituall, &amp; temporal Magiſtrates.</hi> Whereas your Reformation firſt quite caſt off the yoake of the Eccleſiaſtical Superiour, &amp; by degrees ſo weakned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37671:6"/>that of the Ciuil Authority, by perpetual en croachments vpon its <hi>Prerogatiue,</hi> that it broke it too. And then you ſent your <hi>King</hi> to the graue with the formalities of Iuſtice, and pulled the <hi>Lords</hi> out of their ſeates into the loweſt ranks of the People, annulling all the Priuiledges of <hi>Peeres,</hi> &amp; equalling them with the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of the <hi>Commons.</hi> This done how mercifully you dealt with <hi>Lords, Gentlemen,</hi> &amp; <hi>Commons,</hi> appeares by the hyſtory of thoſe times, &amp; many ſtill aliue can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Shew ſuch an example of exorbitant Tyranny in any <hi>Catholick nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. We muſt not ſay it is only the Duty of <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Governours,</hi> but of euery particular man in his way &amp; meaſure, to lend his helping hand to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of ſo good a work, &amp; to do what he can for the mantaining of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion &amp; worſhip of God in its <hi>Primitiue Purity,</hi> which Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles taught.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer: your words here ſeeme as ſmooth as oyle; yet they are Darts, Darts shot at the very hart of Government: for they encouraged and authorize each priuate man to meddle with the Church Diſcipline, &amp; order, euen the <hi>Altar,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he phanſies the ancient <hi>worship of God,</hi> in its <hi>Primitiue Purity:</hi> to which People are prone enough of themſelues. Euery one is willing to deferr to the Phyſitian, to the Lawyer, &amp; euen to the ſmith, or Cobler in their owne Art: yet in matter of Church, or ſtate, euery one thinks himſelf wiſer, then thoſe who ſit at the Helme, &amp; ſufficiently qualifyed to correct them: &amp; being once imbued with this opinion, that <hi>it is the Duty of each Priuate man to lend a hand, to further the worke of the Lord, &amp; mantaine the Church in its Purity, as eſtablisht by Chriſt,</hi> it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follows, that each one preſume to direct his Superiour, to what he likes, take vpon him to gouerne, whoſe rank is to be gouerned, &amp; by that meanes he will breake the order eſtabliſht, diſorder the Counſils of the Magiſtrate, hinder his Actings, &amp; diſturbe, or diſſolue the Gouernment. No way more Innocent for ſubjects to repreſent their minds to ſuperiours, then by <hi>Petitions:</hi> yet theſe are declared <hi>ſeditious</hi> by the Judges, &amp; found ſuch by Practice, becauſe the People are taught (as the late King of Glorious memory ſayd) <hi>firſt to Petition, then to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, then to dictate, at laſt to command, &amp; ouer aye the Parliament,</hi> &amp; all lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. To prevent which miſcheifes to the Publick, with great reaſon <hi>Petitious</hi> haue been of late forbidden by Proclamation.</p>
               <p>How much more Peaceable are the ways of <hi>Catholiks,</hi> who are taught to leaue the care of prouiding for publicke ſecurity in Church, &amp; ſtate to the lawfull ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours of both, &amp; to obey them in all things, where there appeares no ſin?</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. <hi>My Lord of Shaftesbury,</hi> your Pious &amp; Conſtant <hi>Zeale</hi> for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> hath euer been very remarkable; &amp; it is ſo much the more improued now, as your Lordship ſees it in a moſt deſperate, &amp; languishing condition.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ: what you meane by <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> I know not: (it is as hard to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37671:6"/>frame a Definition of it, as to make a gowne for the moone, in the Fable) &amp; I beleiue you know as litle what has been, or is that noble man's Faith, or if he hath any. By what I heare of his paſt life, I dare ſay, that if the <hi>English Proteſtant Bishops</hi> take ſtrict informations of it, they will ſcarce <hi>canonize</hi> him. And why you should repreſent the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> in ſuch a gaſping condition, I know not. <hi>Papiſts</hi> cannot haue reduced it ſo low, who are by it reduced almoſt to nothing: their Preiſts executed, impriſoned, or fled: if any remaine, to conceale them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from your <hi>Argos</hi> eyes, they are forced to ly hidden, as the Primitiue Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in dens, caues, &amp; woods: their nobility impriſoned, their gently banisht, their houſes ranſacked, their eſtates confiſcated, &amp; you poore remainder of them ſcarce ſecure of one day's, nay one hours liberty. And what hurt can ſuch a shattred, defeated, deſpicable body of men do to the <hi>Triumphant Proteſtant Church?</hi> This repreſentation of its diſmal condition, is but your old ſtratagem, to ſtir vp the rabble to ſedition, to preuent its vtter ruin, which by ſuch tragicall beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings you effected in 42. &amp; now endeauour it againe. For before you told your Reader, that each priuate man is bound to lend a hand to hold vp the Arke, when it is in danger of falling: now you ſay, it is in moſt imminent danger. What fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, but that at this time each priuate man is bound to fall to worke to protect <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> &amp; do what he can to mantaine it? Which if it be not ſeditious, I know not what is.</p>
               <p>I obſerue generally in all your Libels againſt <hi>Catholiks,</hi> that in your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces, (which are writ with moſt Art, &amp; red with moſt Attention) you always haue ſome deſperate fling at the <hi>Preſent Gouernment:</hi> as if your prime deſign were to ruin that, which breares the firſt brunt in all you attacks. I think without caſting a figure, we may gueſſe at your intentions.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. I can no better acquit my ſelfe of my Duty (to preſerue the life of gaſping <hi>Protentantiſme</hi>) then by pulling of the maſque, &amp; rectifying the Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thoſe that are not too much <hi>bigotted</hi> to the <hi>Roman</hi> communion, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing them of the cruelty, &amp; Bloodineſs of their Doctrines, &amp; Principles.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ: It ſeemes if others neglect theirs, you will comply with your Duty, &amp; here you giue vs a ſummary of your whole booke: which containes a great charge againſt vs, if true; &amp; if falſe, as great a charge againſt your ſelf, who pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish ſuch a calumny, &amp; againſt your Church, which approues, &amp; applauds it. I hope to make it euident that you pull no <hi>maske</hi> off of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but which you put on them, &amp; which they deteſt as much, as you or any <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. I could wish, that care might be taken, that <hi>Papiſts</hi> children ſhould not ſucke in this ſo dangerous a Religion to the Peace of the ſtate; with their Milke, but that they should be baptized after our way, &amp; educated in the <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Proteſtantiſme.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37671:7"/>
               <p>Anſ: here we ſee your own <hi>meekeneſſe,</hi> whileſt you reproach <hi>Cruelty</hi> to vs: for althô the laws enacted againſt vs, &amp; of late executed with ſuch ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, be ſayd by ſtrangers to be written, like thoſe of <hi>Draco,</hi> with Bloud, yet they do not ſatisfy you, who require a further law, to take away all our children to be bred vp in <hi>Proteſtantiſm.</hi> A thing ſo contrary to the law of nature, &amp; ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, that it neuer was practiſed; not euen in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, vpon the <hi>Iews.</hi> Thus you <hi>inhance the Honour &amp; credit of your Religion, which is made vp of Loue, &amp; charity, &amp; a ſweete condeſcenſion, &amp; Peaceableneſſe of mind to all Men.</hi> Which are your words. You <hi>affect the voice of Iacob; but we ſeele the hands of Eſau.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER 2. English Catholicks do not hold <hi>Murther</hi> Lawfull.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. I cannot but wonder, they (the Papiſts) should be to far loſt ſo all Humanity, &amp; ſenſe of Pity, as to hold that moſt damnable Tenet of <hi>Murther,</hi> &amp; <hi>Treaſon,</hi> not only to be <hi>lawfull;</hi> but in many, if not moſt caſes, to be <hi>neceſſary, commendable,</hi> &amp; <hi>meritorious.</hi> Now that they hold theſe four Points in <hi>Murther</hi> &amp; <hi>Treaſon</hi> I ſhall proue it palpably vpon them, from the Teſtimony of their owne writings.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer: you may with reaſon wonder at the <hi>Inhumamanity</hi> of <hi>English Papiſts,</hi> if this charge be true: &amp; we may wonder you should haue loſt all shame of men, if it be falſe. The charge is generall, &amp; involues all <hi>Catholicks:</hi> ſo it muſt be falſe &amp; vnjuſt, if any be innocent: for two contradictions cannot be true: viz: <hi>All</hi> Papiſts <hi>hold Murther, &amp; Treaſon lawfull, neceſſary,</hi> &amp;c. And: <hi>ſome</hi> Papiſts <hi>haue no ſuch opinions of Murther, and Treaſon.</hi> Yet both Propoſitions are your own: the firſt, in the words aboue cited: the ſecond, page 5. where you haue theſe words: <hi>I will not be ſo adventurous, as to ſay or think, there are none amongſt them of a leſse, ſavage Temper, &amp; diſpoſition.</hi> Which are contradictory to the generall char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, as owning ſome <hi>Papiſts</hi> to be free from thoſe opinions of <hi>Murther,</hi> &amp; <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſeldome find any of the <hi>Proteſtant Miniſters</hi> ſpeake without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, when <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Popery</hi> is the ſubiect of their diſcourſe: becauſe there are two contrary inclinations in their wills, the one of <hi>loue to Truth,</hi> the other of <hi>hatred to Popery &amp; Papiſts.</hi> The firſt is ſo naturall to all men, that they cannot to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37671:7"/>free themſelues from it: <hi>Quid amplius deſiderat anima, quam veritatem?</hi> Aug. tract. 26. in Ioan. The ſecond is ſo tenaciouſly retained, for what motiue I know not, but leaue to them to declare) that it workes commonly more violently, &amp; controwles the loue of Truth, althô it cannot quite banish it out of their Harts: for this finds ſome occaſions to make them giue Glory to God, &amp; acknowledg the innocency of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> which the other repreſents as the worſt of men. I will proue this out of this very pamphlet.</p>
               <p>Page 9 &amp; 10. I find theſe, words: <hi>Are they,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts, not men like the reſt of Mankind? Haue they not the ſame Paſsion, &amp; Tempers, the ſame Impulſes of Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes, &amp; pity in their Nature with others of different Iudgments, &amp; perſwaſions? — Take them out of that Character</hi> (their Religion) <hi>&amp; they are in all things like vnto the reſt of their Fellow-Creatures, &amp; Brethren; their minds are Peaceable, their Deportment affable &amp; Generous &amp; the Gros of their Tempers full of a ſweet, &amp; indearing Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</hi> Yet Page 17. you ſay — <hi>Their Tempers are Fire &amp; Toe.</hi> And in the very ſame place, where you commend our natures &amp; Tempers ſo much, you ſay: <hi>Their Religion forces them to put off their Humanity, &amp; makes them ſo bloody minded as therein to be farr worſe then beaſts that perish.</hi> And a little after: <hi>No Tygers are more fell, &amp; ſavage then they in their Natures: they could cut off the whole race of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an kind: — they could call downe fire from Heauen, nay the very ſtames of Hell on all ſuch, as would not bend the knee to their BAAL, &amp; adjuſt their Faith &amp; Conſciences to the wild Caprichio of their Idolatrous Enthuſiaſmes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How with Truth to reconcile theſe different chatacters of vs, I cannot tell. That <hi>our Minds</hi> ſhould <hi>be Peaceable;</hi> &amp; <hi>yet we be bloody minded:</hi> we <hi>like the reſt of Mankind</hi> &amp; yet <hi>haue put off our Humanity our Deportments affable &amp; generous;</hi> &amp; yet <hi>we more fell, &amp; ſauage, then the Tygers. Our Tempers full of a ſweete &amp; Indearing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency;</hi> &amp; yet <hi>our Tempers should be fire &amp; toe.</hi> In reality as theſe contradictions can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand together, ſo they diſcouer clearly thoſe two contrary Paſſions in your breaſt of <hi>loue to Truth,</hi> &amp; <hi>hatred to Papiſts.</hi> The firſt ſpeakes aduantageouſly of vs, the ſecond blames vs: this condemnes, that abſolues vs. The firſt is euidently true, &amp; viſible to all, who conuerſe with vs; the ſecond ſurmized only by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. Juſt ſo the <hi>Pagans</hi> perſecuted the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of their times. <hi>Caius</hi> is a good man; but his Religion ſpoyles all: <hi>Titius</hi> is a Peaceable man; but he is a Chriſtian: ſuch &amp; ſuch are ciuil, &amp; honeſt good natured men; but they deuour Children, commit inceſt with their Mothers, &amp; ſiſters, &amp;c. <hi>Laudant, quae ſciunt,</hi> ſayd T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtul. Apol. c. 3. <hi>vituperant quae ignorant: &amp; id quod ſciunt, eo quod ignorant corrumpunt. Cum ſit iuſtius occulta de manifeſtis praeiudicare quam manifeſta de occultis praedamnare. They commend what they know certainly &amp; find by experience; they blame what they ſurmize, &amp; feigne of vs: and they bereaue vs of the good name due to our known vertues, by reproaching
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37671:8"/>vnto vs ſuch vnknown vices. Whereas in Iuſtice they should, rather iudge favourably of our known hidden actions by reaſon of our publick vertuous liues, then condemne our vertues, for faults only ſurmized.</hi> Thus <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Whence it appeares that in your calumnies you imitate the Pagans; &amp; we follow the example of the Primitiue Chriſtians in our Apologies.</p>
               <p>You ſay we allow of <hi>Murther</hi> &amp; <hi>Treaſon:</hi> we declare that we deteſt them: &amp; we proue this deteſtation of them from our Diuine &amp; Humane, Ciuil, &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical laws. The command not to kill, is extant in our Bibles, our Canons, &amp; our Codes, we teach it to children in our Catechiſmes, to Schollers in our leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; to all men in our Sermons. The Catholick <hi>Church</hi> punish <hi>Murther,</hi> with <hi>Irregularity,</hi> Catholick <hi>States</hi> with <hi>Death,</hi> &amp; Catholick <hi>Faith,</hi> with <hi>Hell fire,</hi> if it not be repented Nay voluntarily expoſing a mans ſelf to a probable danger of <hi>Murther,</hi> in a <hi>Duel,</hi> is Death without remiſſion in <hi>France,</hi> where Catholick Religion ſtill preuailes, &amp; <hi>Ieſuits</hi> are to be found. Laſtly our English laws againſt <hi>Murther</hi> were made by our Catholick anceſtors. What greater euidence can you giue of a Deteſtation of <hi>Murther,</hi> &amp; <hi>horrour of Bloud,</hi> then we haue giuen, &amp; do ſtillgiue?</p>
               <p>You ground your accuſation cheifly on the ſayings of ſome writers, whoſe ſentiments shall be examined in the next Chapter: where I doubt not to make it euident that you impoſe on them things, which they neuer held. Till then (to ſhew how vnſufficient your proofes are) I will gratis admit, that they truly taught, what you falſly ſay they did. What is that to the <hi>English Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> (whome you accuſe, &amp; I defend , who neuer read their workes, know nothing of their Doctrine, &amp; (probably) neuer heard their names? will you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> for one <hi>Iudas:</hi> all the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for one Inceſtuous man, all the Deacons, for one <hi>Nicolas:</hi> all the neophits, for one <hi>Simon:</hi> all in the Ark for one <hi>Cham:</hi> all men for one <hi>Cain,</hi> &amp; all Angels for one <hi>Lucifer?</hi> you can heare (ſays S. Auſtin Epiſt. 137.) your Neighbour's wife hath broken her Faith to him, without comdemning your Mothers or ſiſters maryed, or turning your own wiues out of dores, &amp; though your freind's ſon take bad courſes, yet you do not braine your own, nor preſent them as <hi>Felons</hi> at the Aſſizes. Why ſhould then the <hi>English Catholiks</hi> be arraigned as holding <hi>Murther</hi> lawfull, becauſe <hi>Leſsius</hi> at <hi>Louen,</hi> or <hi>Amieus</hi> at <hi>Gretz,</hi> taught it, althô they neuer heard any thing of the Doctrine, nor men, nor townes where they reſided. You will ſay, it may be they know, &amp; approue it (that is the moſt your can draw out of this argument) &amp; I anſwer it may be, &amp; certainly is moſt commonly ſo, that they neither ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, nor knew of it. What ground here for arraignment? In <hi>Treaſon</hi> the will is reputed for the Fact, &amp; both punisht alike: not ſo in <hi>Felony.</hi> Would you haue <hi>Catholicks</hi> condemned on much leſſe ground then a <hi>will to Murther,</hi> for <hi>a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37671:8"/>thought of it?</hi> nay for the <hi>poſsibility of a thought?</hi> For all you can infer out of the ſentiments of thoſe Authours, is that it is poſſible, <hi>English Catholicks</hi> may haue the like ſentiments.</p>
               <p>Againe: if there be ſuch a communication of bad works amongſt all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, that each one muſt be anſwerable for all the faults of any other, althô vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to him (for this you muſt ſay if you ſay any thing) why is there not a like communication of good? <hi>Leſsius</hi> ſay you allows <hi>Murther,</hi> to ſaue a mans ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: another condemnes this. Why ſhall not this man's writing againſt it be as efficacious to abſolue me, as the others writing for it, to condemne me: when I neuer gaue you any cauſe to ſuſpect I frame my conſcience either in ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or practice, rather according to the allower, then the condemner of <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And which is yet more conuincing, not only priuate Perſons haue declared their diſlike of theſe Doctrines; but ſeueral vniuerſities, &amp; Biſhops haue cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, &amp; the Pope hath condemned them. I ſay thoſe very Propoſitions which you cite out of <hi>Molina, Leſsius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Amicus.</hi> That of <hi>Amicus,</hi> that <hi>it is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for an Eccleſiaſtick to kill a Detractor,</hi> was condemned by <hi>Alexander</hi> VII. 24. Sept. 1665. Thoſe of <hi>Molina,</hi> &amp; <hi>Leſsius,</hi> that it is <hi>lawfull to kill to ſaue our honour,</hi> by <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. 2. March 1679. which decrees are enforced with an Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all ſuch as dare diſobey. Now I ſuppoſe you know, that all true <hi>Catholicks</hi> obey the <hi>Popes</hi> decrees in Doctrinal matters; &amp; how euer they take the freedome to Iudge of things, before any Declaration of the Church, or her head vnder <hi>Chriſt</hi> on Earth, yet when any decree is publiſht, we all lay down our priuate ſentiments, &amp; frame both Actions, &amp; conſcience according to that venerable rule. With what Iuſtice then can you charge any with thoſe Doctrines which we all do renounce, and are bound to do ſo, vnder paine of Excommunication?</p>
               <p>Laſtly I appeale to the Experience of <hi>English Proteſtants,</hi> who haue trauelled: let them ſay, whither in <hi>Flanders, France,</hi> or euen <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf they found the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſuch <hi>Bloud thirſty Ruffians,</hi> as you deſcribe them. A Miniſter, who had preacht in <hi>England,</hi> that the Pope was <hi>the Beaſt of the Apocalypſe,</hi> had <hi>ſeuen heads, &amp; ten hornes,</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming afterwards to <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; being admitted to the preſence of the Pope, who had heard of it, the Pope ſayd to him: <hi>Come hither ſon, view me well, ſee that I haue but one head, &amp; neuer a horne at all: looke vpon my head,</hi> (which he then vncouered) <hi>&amp; feele it, &amp; beleiue your owne eyes, that I am no ſuch a monſter, as you in England deſcribe me.</hi> This was <hi>Vrbaen</hi> VIII. Another of the ſame tribe, tooke the liberty in <hi>Rome</hi> amongſt the Natiues to declaime againſt the Pope: who hearing of it, ſent one to aduiſe him to be more wary in his words: <hi>for althô, ſayd he, there shall be no publick procedure againſt you, yet I cannot aſſure, but that you may receiue ſome diſpleaſure from ſome of my ſubjects.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:37671:9"/>
               <p>As for <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> whome you repreſent as moſt addicted to <hi>Murthering Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> I neuer heard any complaint of Inciuilities receiued from them, and I haue heard ſeuerall trauellers &amp; Marchants acknowledge fauours receiued by their meanes euen in <hi>Spaine, Italy,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Indies.</hi> Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> your Oracle, hath done nothing in <hi>England,</hi> which he did not deſign at <hi>S. Omers:</hi> &amp; with his vſuall diſcretion diſcouered there that black hellish deſign. Mr. <hi>Whitebread</hi> then Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincial knew this very well, &amp; ſpoke of it with much anguiſh to ſome aliue, who can witneſs it, foreſeing what miſcheif might be feared, when that man's mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lying humour ſhould ioyn with the <hi>Popular Odium</hi> of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> &amp; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>Ieſuites.</hi> Then, or neuer there was occaſion to practice vpon him that caſe of <hi>Amicus,</hi> had the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> approued it. Yet no ſuch thing was thought on: the <hi>Prouincial</hi> ordred him a decent ſute of Cloths, and four pounds ſterling to beare his charges to <hi>London,</hi> &amp; ſent him away with all poſſible charity, to ſee whither he could by that ſweeten his malignity, &amp; <hi>ouercome Euil with good.</hi> Rom 12.21.</p>
               <p>This, this is the way, which <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> vſe towards their enemies: thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they learne our of the Ghoſpel, &amp; their Rules: this their Superiours recommend, this they practice, to heape hot <hi>Coales</hi> vpon their Ennemies, not to burne the leaſt haire of their heads; but to warme their harts with the fire of the loue of God, which will introduce that of their Neighbour.</p>
               <p>And that the <hi>English Catholicks</hi> are bred vp with the ſame peaceable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, appeares by their Patient ſuffering whatſoeuer <hi>Oates,</hi> &amp; his <hi>Aſſociates</hi> haue acted in purſuance of his Majeſty's order, but beyond his commiſſion, &amp; contrary to his mercifull intentions: althô their cruel Actions haue been accompanyed with inſulting barbarous words, which are much more greiuous to a generous mind, then the Actions themſelues. All which haue met with no other return, but prayers for his Sacred Majeſty, &amp; euen for thoſe inſtruments of God's wrath vpon the Nation. I ſay <hi>the Nation,</hi> which in reality ſuffers more, then Catholicks, (who ſeeme the greateſt, &amp; only ſufferers in this Tragedy) for, <hi>Non qui patitur: ſed qui facit iniuriam miſer eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I now appeale to your ſelf, ſir, what hath appeared in all this sharpe &amp; tedious tryall of the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> which doth confirm the Character, you giue of them; viz: that their <hi>Tempers are Fire, &amp; Toe</hi> that they haue caſt off their <hi>Humanity are more fell &amp; ſauage then Tigers, worſe then the Beaſt which perish,</hi> &amp;c. To confute theſe Impudent calumnies, nothing is neceſſary, but to looke on our liues. <hi>Apologias non ſcribimus, ſed viuimus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37671:9"/>
               <head>CHAPTER 3. The Ieſuits cited by E. C. doe not teach <hi>Murther</hi> to be lawfull.</head>
               <p>I haue hitherto admitted your aſſertion to be tru that thoſe Ieſuites, you cite, did teach <hi>Murther</hi> to be <hi>Lawfull,</hi> yet that the <hi>English Catholicks</hi> were vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it: &amp; that there is not the leaſt colour of Reaſon, or Iuſtice, to charge it on them. I now come to examin that aſſertion, &amp; if your proofs faile you there too, then I hope you will own, that your Bill ought not to be found.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. 2. <hi>Leſsius</hi> de Juſt. l. 2. c. 9. d. 12. n. 79 ſaies <hi>that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> who hath receiued a box oth Ear, may be permitted to ſtrike againe, for the auoiding of infamy &amp; to that end may immediatly put bucke the Injury, &amp; that with his ſword, etiam cum gladio.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer 1. thoſe are not the words of <hi>Leſsius;</hi> but taken by him out of <hi>Victoria de Iure Belli</hi> n. 8.</p>
               <p>Anſ. 2. <hi>Leſsius</hi> condemnes that opinion: for he ſays n. 80. <hi>Haec ſententia non videtur in praxi facile permittenda. This opinion is not eaſily to be followed:</hi> &amp; giues two very good reaſons why it is not to be practiſed.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. It doth not appeare out of thoſe words, that the Authour of them ſpeakes of killing, neither doth the vſe of the ſword ſignifye that: ſeing a ſword may be vſed 1. for our defence. 2. to fright an aduerſary. 3. to bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te him, <hi>Au plat d'Eſpée</hi> ſay the french, 4. to giue ſome ſlyght wound not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, either with point, or edge.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 4. Whoſoeuer taught that opinion, &amp; what euer his meaning was, all <hi>Catholikcs,</hi> &amp; particularly <hi>Ieſuites</hi> renounce it: for <hi>Innnocent</hi> XI. expreſſely condemned it. And all the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> in the world ſubmit to that decree.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. Page 3. <hi>Leſsius</hi> l. 2. c. 9. d. 12. n. 77. ſays: <hi>If you endeauour to ruin my reputation by opprobrious ſpeeches, ſpoken before perſons of Honour, &amp; that I cannot auoyde them other ways then by killing you, I may: nay thô the crime you lay to my charge be ſuch as I am really guilty of, it being ſuppoſed to be ſo ſecretly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that you cannot diſcouer it according to the ways of Iuſtice.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. 1. <hi>Leſsius</hi> hath not thoſe words, nor any bearing the ſame ſence in that place, nor any where elſe in his whole workes. And I challenge you, &amp;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37671:10"/>all your brethren to diſproue this, by ſhewing them.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. <hi>Leſsius</hi> in that place ſpeakes of an opinion allowing <hi>a man of honour</hi> to kill <hi>a raskal,</hi> who cudgels, or buffets him, if there be no other meanes to auoyde the <hi>diſgrace.</hi> And afterwards, n. 78. he condemnes that opinion: <hi>Haec ſententia non eſt ſequenda,</hi> ſays he: <hi>this opinion ought not to be followed. For it ought to ſuffice, that verbal iniuries be put by with words, &amp; that iniurious Actions may be punisht by courſe of Iuſtice.</hi> Thus <hi>Leſsius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. All Catholicks condemne that opinion, it hauing been condemned by <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. Thus much for <hi>Leſsius.</hi> The next <hi>Ieſuit</hi> you produce is <hi>Molina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. page 2. by <hi>Molina</hi> the life of a man is reckened at ſix or ſeuen Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kats: &amp; he aſſures vs, <hi>that it is lawfull to kill him for it, nay thô he, who hath taken them, fly for it: adding further in the ſame place, that he durſt not charge that man with any ſin, that kills another, who had taken from him a thing of the value of a crown, or leſſe, vnius aurei, vel minoris adhuc valoris.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. 1. If he reckons a Man's life at 6. or 7. Dukats, he rates it much higher then our <hi>English Laws,</hi> who recken it at 13. <hi>pence-half penny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. you confound two caſes in <hi>Molina, one of a theif who comes to rob you.</hi> The other <hi>of one who hath robbed you, &amp; runs away with your purſe, or goods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the firſt, he ſays, that if a theif ſets vpon you, &amp; threatens to kill you, if you do not deliver your mony <hi>(be it but a Crowne or leſſe)</hi> that you may defend your life, &amp; mony; &amp; if in the fight, you chance to kill him, he dares not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem you. I do not think our laws in <hi>England</hi> would hang one, who should in that manner kill a Hygh-way man on the road. If they would, they are very fauourable to theiues.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond caſe he anſwears, that if the theif run away with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiderable ſumme (fiue Duckats he eſteemes as nothing) &amp; there be little hopes to recouer it, hauing called in vaine to him, to reſtore the goods, it is lawfull to ſhoot at him, yet ſo as to auoyde giuing him a mortal wound. <hi>Semper conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendum eſt, ne proximus occidatur,</hi> are his words. Then he ſays, if by chance the theif dye of that wound, <hi>non auderem condemnare.</hi> I dare not condemne the Man as a <hi>Murtherer,</hi> to the paines appointed by law to ſuch. This I ſpeake not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing the opinion; but only to explicate his meaning, &amp; to shew how you haue wronged him 1. in confounding two different caſes, &amp; 2 in miſ-repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his meaning in both. But as to the thing, or opinion itſelf.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. both I, &amp; all <hi>Papiſts</hi> deteſt the opinion, &amp; condem the practice of it, in obedience to the Decree often cited of Innocent XI.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. Pag. 3. <hi>Amicus</hi> tom. 5. Diſp. 36. n. 118. <hi>It is Lawfull for an Eccleſiaſtick, or a Religious Man, to kill a Detractor, that but threatens to diuulge th
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37671:10"/>ſcandalous crimes of his Community, when there is no other means left to himder him from doing of it, as if he be ready to ſcatter his Calumnys, if not ſuddenly diſpatched out of the way.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer 1. <hi>Amicus</hi> his fault in aduancing that Propoſition was greate: althô he corrected the malignity of it, by adding that he did affirme nothing; but left his Diſcourſe to the judgment of the diſcreet Reader.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 2. in the <hi>Antwerpe</hi> Edition of <hi>Amicus</hi> an. 1650. made by <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> that whole diſcourſe was left out: &amp; by order of the General of the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> it was blotted out of all copyes of the firſt edition in the Libraries of the <hi>Ieſuites.</hi> By both which actions the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> haue ſufficiently declared their diſowning of that Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 3. that ſame Propoſition was condemned by <hi>Alexander</hi> VII. on the 24. <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1665. from which time, all Catholicks, haue been obliged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of Excommunication to diſown that Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Thus much in vindication of the three <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> you cite: out of which three things are euident.</p>
               <p>The 1. that not one of them taught the Doctrine you charge them with. Two poſitiuely teach the contrary: &amp; the third leaues the Iudgment to the Reader.</p>
               <p>The 2. that if they had erred, no <hi>English Catholick</hi> would be concerned in it, 1. becauſe they knew nothing of the Doctrine. &amp; 2. becauſe they beleiue, &amp; practice the quite contrary.</p>
               <p>The 3. no Catholick in the world can be charged with thoſe doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they being condemned by the Church, &amp; all Catholicks owning obedience to thoſe <hi>Decrees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. <hi>Soto</hi> ſays in defence of his perſon, a man aſſaulted may kill another: &amp; ſays, that to hold it not Lawfull in ſuch a caſe, (thô to the ruin of the man's ſoul to boot) <hi>is both to peruert the law of nature, &amp; to render the ſweet, &amp; eaſy yoake of Chriſt intolerable.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>Soto</hi> l. 5. de Juſti: q 1. ar. 8. propoſes this queſtion: <hi>Whither it be lawfull to kill another in my own defence.</hi> And he anſwers 1. <hi>When I can ſane my own life without killing the aggreſſor, I muſt not kill him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>When I cannot eſcape without killing the Aggreſſor, I may kill him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>It is neuer lawfull for any priuate man to intend the Death of another.</hi> That being permitted only to abſolute Princes, &amp; Souueraign ſtates, &amp; by their order to their officers, ſouldiers in time of war, &amp; Executioners. What diſpleaſes you in this. Doth not our English Laws permit a man to kill an aggreſſor, who h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th driuen him to a wall, ſoe as he can not ſaue his life by flight? &amp; what is that, but <hi>Soto</hi>'s 2. <hi>concluſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37671:11"/>
               <p>Then he propoſes this obiection againſt his 2. Concluſion. The aggreſſor is in ſtate of mortal ſin, becauſe he ſeekes my life. Wherefore if I kill him, he will be damned, as dying in mortal ſin. Now I am bound to looſe my life rather then his ſoul: <hi>ergo,</hi> I muſt let my ſelf be killed. And he ſays, if this reaſon were good, it were neuer lawfull for any man to defend his life from any <hi>Aggreſſor,</hi> who preſſeth beyond all poſſibility of eſcape. Which duty, to lett my ſelf be killed, being contrary to the law of nature, ſo fauourable to <hi>Ruffians,</hi> &amp; ſo hard for <hi>Innocent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſons,</hi> it would make the ſweete yoake of <hi>Chriſt</hi> vneaſy, &amp; intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>To cleere his meaning, I propoſe another caſe: ſuppoſe a Captain of one of his Majeſty's ſhips, ſhould ſcruple to shoot bullets at the <hi>Algerins,</hi> as thinking it more conformable to the law of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to let his ſhip be taken then to ſaue it by the <hi>Death,</hi> &amp; <hi>Damnation</hi> of thoſe <hi>Infidels.</hi> What anſwer would you E. C. giue? that he ought to yeild his ship to auoyde the loſſe of thoſe ſouls: &amp; that the law of <hi>Chriſt</hi> obliges to it? If ſo, I beleiue his Majeſty will neuer appoint you to inſtruct his ſeamen. If you ſay, he may vſe ſuch meanes as God, &amp; his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce haue furniſht him with for the defence of his ſhip, althô by that meanes ſome <hi>Algerins</hi> be killed, &amp; their ſouls loſt: for Chriſt's law would be intolerable to Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Powers, if it enjoined the contrary; if I ſay you anſwer ſo, you ſay as much as <hi>Soto</hi> ſays.</p>
               <p>Not to tire my Reader with vneceſſary matter. &amp; repetitions, I omit what you cite out of <hi>Nauar, Graſſü,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bonacina.</hi> One word ſuffices for all: either they truly approue of <hi>Murther,</hi> or they do not. If they do, we diſown them: &amp; ſo you haue no right to charge their ſentiments on vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER 4. Proteſtants both teach, &amp; practice ſedition &amp; Rebellion.</head>
               <p>IT is with the greateſt reluctance imaginable that I rake in this kennel, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof the fumes &amp; ſtench is able to infect a People ſo ſuſceptible of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as English are. Jt were to be wisht theſe ſeditious maximes had neuer appeared in the world, or that vpon their firſt appearance, that ſeuerity had been vſed on them, which the Roman Senat practiſed on Monſters, that they had
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37671:11"/>been tranſported out of the fight of men, &amp; butyed in perpetuall obliuion. The G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nerals of the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> haue often forbidden their ſubjects to treate of any of theſe ſeditious points, leaſt by writing of them, their memory might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued; which is always dangerous, when People are diſpoſed to practice them. And I doubt not but experience will ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w, that is the moſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent way, to preuent all miſcheife. Yet to comply with your importunity, I will follow &amp; encounter you in this. I owne that there haue been exceſſes on both ſides in their writers, whoſe zeale for the cauſe they embraced was greater, then their Diſcretion. Yet the fault is leſſe in thoſe who ſtand only for what was of old beleiued, and practiſed, then in thoſe, who would haue all things changed according to their phanſy: &amp; therfore the exceſſes on the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> ſide are more excuſable: yet we ſhall find the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> more pragmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, more refractory to Superiours, more violent, more ſeditious, &amp; Rebellious, then <hi>Catholicks</hi> without compariſon. I will begin with your Doctrine, then paſſe to your practice.</p>
               <p>The roote of all our ſeditious maximes is that deteſtable Propoſition of your <hi>Patriark Witlef, no Prince, nor Prelat, nor Biſhop continues ſuch in ſtate of mortal ſin.</hi> Concil Conſtant. f. 8. of which <hi>Melanction</hi> ſayd (Comment. in Polit.) <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ cauſed much miſcheif, by teaching that thoſe looſe all Authority, who haue not the holy Ghoſt.</hi> What <hi>Oates</hi> hath the impudence to ſay euen to his Majeſty is much wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, for he requires not only that <hi>Princes Liue vertucuſly,</hi> (that is haue the Holy Ghoſt) but alſo puniſh all who do not, vnder <hi>paine of Depoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Goodman</hi> in his Apology is of the ſame mind. <hi>Bad Princes according to the Law of God ought to be depoſed,</hi> ſayd he: <hi>&amp; in caſe the Magiſtrates neglect to doe their Duty, the People haue as free liberty to do it, as if there were no Magiſtrates at all, &amp; in thoſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of time, God enlargeth them with liberty to vſe the ſword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caluin</hi> in 6. Dan. v. 22. &amp; 25. <hi>The Kings of the Earth doe depriue themſelues of Power, when they make head againſt the King of Heauen. Yea they are vnworthy to be numbred amongſt men: &amp; therefore we are rather to ſpit in their faces, then to obey them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Knox: <hi>If Princes gouerne tyrannically againſt God, &amp; his Truth, their ſubjects are abſolued from their Oath of Fidelity.</hi> But is this freeing from their oath all? No: For</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Buccanan</hi> ſays: <hi>The common People haue right to diſpoſe of the ſcepters of Kingdomes at their pleaſure.</hi> Again: <hi>the People have Power to Iudge of the life of their Kings.</hi> Yet more: <hi>It were to be wisht, that rewards were appointed for ſuch as kill Tyrants, as there are for ſuch as kill wolues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Goodman: Kings haue right to raigne from the People who vpon occaſion can alſo reuoke it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37671:12"/>
               <p>In fine <hi>Oſiander</hi> ſays it is the common opinion of <hi>Wiclef's</hi> followers, <hi>that the People, may, as they shall pleafe, punish their Princes, who offend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe &amp; many other ſeditious Doctrines may be found in the <hi>Proteſtants Apology.</hi> And if any deſire to ſee their number encreaſed by modern Factious Spirits, he ſhall ſee enough in the ordinary Gazets viz: that <hi>the King is one of the three ſtates, that the houſe of Commens made him what he is: that it is not treaſon to beare armes againſt the King, prouided it be not againſt the three ſtates. That the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament CAN DISPOSE of the SVCCESSION of the CROWN:</hi> &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch maximes, which you dayly aduance, of as malignant a Nature as any before cited.</p>
               <p>Here I muſt obſerue a remarkable difference betwixt Catholicks &amp; you: <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> do not follow theſe Principles (I defy you to name any one <hi>Catholick</hi> aliue, who hath taught any of them) &amp; you retaine them ſtill: or rather grow worſe &amp; worſe. Which is of no ſmall conſequence to diſcouer what party is dangerous to the ſtate, which guilty of treaſonable maximes.</p>
               <p>I come now to your practice: which giues reaſon to ſay, you came into the world like the Cadmean brood, all armed: &amp; that many, or rather all your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces felt your armes, aſſoon as they ſaw your faces. In <hi>Geneua</hi> you caſt off the Authority of your Bishop, Prince of the town. In higher <hi>Germany</hi> you ſhaked the authority of <hi>Charles</hi> V. Emperour. In lower <hi>Germany</hi> you withdrew many Prouinces from the obedience of their King. You vſurped vpon <hi>Rudolphus</hi> the Emperour in <hi>Tranſiluania;</hi> vpon <hi>Chriſtiernus,</hi> in <hi>Denmarck;</hi> &amp; vpon <hi>Sigimund,</hi> in <hi>Swedeland.</hi> You fought for the Crowne of <hi>France</hi> againſt <hi>Francis</hi> II. <hi>Charles</hi> IX. &amp; <hi>Henry</hi> III. &amp; in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> IX. you coined mony in the name of one you held for King, ſays Cardinal <hi>Richelieu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs come to our deare Country. In England you ſet vp <hi>Iane Grey,</hi> againſt the lawfull heyre queene <hi>Mary.</hi> You bore armes againſt another <hi>Mary</hi> lawfull queen of <hi>Scotland,</hi> brought her into reſtraint, forced her to depoſe her ſelf, &amp; to fly her country: &amp; not content with keeping her Priſoner nineteen yeares, at laſt you put her barbarouſly to a violent death. Your perpetual inſolencies againſt her ſon &amp; Grandſon, &amp; your encroachments vpon the <hi>Royul Prerogatiue,</hi> are written with a Beame of the ſun. Your whole proceedings againſt <hi>Charles</hi> 1. of Glorious memory, are ſo knowne, that I need not to mind you of them: &amp; ſo deteſtable, that I need no Art to make them appeare odious. I defy you to ſhew, that euer any Catholick deſigned vpon his Souveraigne, what you haue lately acted on yours. Now with what face can you reproach vnto vs any ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Doctrin, whilſt you teach much worſe, &amp; haue executed things more execrable, then euer any <hi>Catholick</hi> dreamt of? Remoue this beame out of your
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37671:12"/>eye, before you take notice of a moth in ours, which yet we haue long ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, as I ſayd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER 5. English Catholicks teach no ſeditious Doctrines.</head>
               <p>E. C. pag. 4. deſcribes vs to be men, <hi>who ſweepe away whole townes, Citties &amp; Nations, ſubuert ſundamental Laws, change Gouernments, cut off Princes, &amp; right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> Monarks, <hi>abſolue ſubjects from their Natural allegiance,</hi> &amp;c &amp; pag 7. he addes: <hi>we are full out ſuch conſtitutioned Perſons as he hath deſcribed vs, &amp; not a jot better: nay if we proue not worſe, before he hath done with vs, we shall be obliged to him for his Ciuility, &amp; Moderation.</hi> A formidable charge: but if we do not tell him it is as great <hi>a lye,</hi> &amp; himſelfe as falſe an Informer, as <hi>Oates,</hi> he ought to thank vs for our <hi>Moderation:</hi> for he brings not one word to proue his accuſation out of any <hi>Engliſh Catholick,</hi> nor of any other countries, aliue: nor any of the dead, who ſpeake <hi>home,</hi> let vs ſee your proofes.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. 4. Peruſe the canon (<hi>c. Excommunicatorum</hi> 23. q. 5.) <hi>we do not account them Murtherers, who burning with the zeal of our Mother the Catholick Church, shall happen to kill any of them.</hi> And are not men of ſuch wicked &amp; bloudy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, like the fatal <hi>Sirius,</hi> or Dogſtar,</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. reade the Canon out, &amp; you will find no ſubiect for this <hi>Tragical Exclamation:</hi> for that very Canon declares that action, <hi>killing an excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated Perſon,</hi> to be a ſin, &amp; commands the Biſhop of <hi>Lucia,</hi> to impoſe vpon the homicide a <hi>ſeuere publick Pennance. Ne eiuſdem Eccleſiae Matres diſciplina deſeratur, Poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam eis indicito congruentem. Leaſt the Diſciplin of our Mother the Church be abandoned, oblige the ſinners to a Pennance proportioned to their offence.</hi> And is this to approue of thoſe attempts? I would willingly ſee your Biſhops impoſe a Pennance on the Rebels, who killed ſeuerall of their fellow ſubjects, loyall to their King: &amp; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they call it <hi>Murther,</hi> or no, I ſhall not trouble them about the word.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. 5. Bellarmin l. 3. de Laicis c. 22. ſays: If it were poſſible, to root out the <hi>Hereticks</hi> (not any in the world excepted, whether KINGS, or EMPEROURS, &amp;c.) without doubt they are to be cut off euery mothers child of them. Is not here enough, (ſurely too much) to eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37671:13"/>how <hi>lawfull</hi> they hold MVRTHER to be? But if it cannot be done becauſe they are too hard, they muſt lye ſtill.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer. It is hard to heape together more malicious falſications in ſo few words. Bellarmin in that place enquires whither thoſe words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Mat. 13.30. <hi>Let the good ſeed &amp; the tares grow vntill the Harueſt,</hi> do not forbid the Execution of malefactors in general: for he ſays, that by the <hi>good ſeede</hi> are vnderſtood all good men, &amp; by <hi>tares</hi> all wicked men: according to thoſe words: <hi>the good ſeede are the children of the Kingdome: tares are the children of the wicked one.</hi> verſu 38. And he ſays that malefactors of what kind ſoeuer, are to be punisht, when it may be done without danger to the publick: but when they are ſo numerous, as to cope with the bulke of loyal ſubjects, they ought to be ſpared, to auoyde greater euil. Which is ſo conformable to common ſence, that none, but ſuch a <hi>momus,</hi> as E. C. could reprehend it: &amp; it is practiſed in all ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. 1. If they can all crush a Rebellion in the egge, by the Death of one, or a few Traitors. 2. Is it ſpread ouer a greate part of the Nation, ſome few heads are punisht, the reſt are pardoned: &amp; 3. ſome times <hi>propter bonum pacts,</hi> the heads themſelues are pardonned too. <hi>Charles</hi> 1. deſigned the firſt, when he ſought the fiue members: &amp; offred the third, when he was a Priſoner. And <hi>Charles</hi> 11. at his happy Reſtauration practiſed the ſecond: for he punisht his Father's judges, &amp; pardonned the reſt.</p>
               <p>Now I come to ſcore vp ſome of your <hi>Falſifications.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſpeakes only of <hi>Hereticks.</hi> He ſpeakes of all kinds of <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facters. Quaeſtio eſt vel de Haereticis, vel de furibus, vel de alijs malis, an extirpandi ſint The doubt is ether of Hereticks, or Thieues, or other Malefactors: whither they be to be cut off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That he doth not except <hi>Kings,</hi> or <hi>Emperours</hi> &amp; to make your Impertinence more obſeruable, you put theſe names in Capital letters. Sir, I neuer thought it neceſſary to except Kings, when we ſpeake of <hi>punishing Rogues, &amp; theiues:</hi> becauſe no man in his wits will think them meant by thoſe words. I beleiue on the ſame ſcore all our <hi>English laws</hi> may be arraigned for I do not think, when they order <hi>a theif to be hanged, a Knyght of the Poſt to looſ his eares:</hi> &amp;c. that they adde except he be a <hi>King or Emperour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 That <hi>Bellarmin</hi> teaches by thoſe words MURTHER to be <hi>lawfull.</hi> Is the <hi>Execution of Felons,</hi> by due courſe of law, <hi>Murther?</hi> of that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſpeakes.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Gentle Reader: I earneſtly deſire thee, to haue ſome Chriſtian compaſſion of the condition of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> thy country-men, &amp; neyghbours who vpon ſuch malicious mis-repreſentations of moſt innocent ſayings, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to publick Hatred, &amp; cruel Perſecutions, by a ſenſeleſſe, vnchriſtian,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37671:13"/>diſingenious ſort of men, whoſe minds are blacker, then their coates: &amp; who make as little bones of a lye, &amp; ſwearing to it, as drinking a glaſſe of ſmal bee when they are thirſty.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. 5. Their Religion tempts them to all Actions that are horrible againſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by giuing them their Lands, &amp; Eſtates, which aſſoone as they haue exterminated <hi>Hereticks,</hi> they ſhall poſſeſſe without controul. <hi>Concil, Later. ſub Innoc.</hi> III. c. 3. Now Council's decrees are by <hi>Papiſts</hi> honoured as Oracles of the Holy Ghoſt. Says <hi>Stapleton.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer. No body is ignorant how variouſly that Canon is ſpoken of. <hi>Platina</hi> ſays that Council made no decrees. Others ſay Abſolute Princes are not comprehended, becauſe not named as they ought to be by reaſon of their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular dignity, <hi>in odioſis, C. ſedes Apoſtolica, de Reſcriptis:</hi> jndeed the words <hi>ſeruato iure Domini principalis, preſeruing entire the right of the ſupreame Lord,</hi> ſhews that the Canon ſpeakes only of <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> or <hi>ſubordinate Princes;</hi> not of the Abſolute, as Kings. Jt is alſo, ſayd that the Kings conſented to the Law, by their Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, &amp; they may enact what pleaſed. Laſtly it is only a poſitiue law: which may be repealed, &amp; doth not oblige vntill it be receiued in the ſeuerall Catholick ſtates. As appeares by thoſe of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent:</hi> which are vniuerſally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued no where.</p>
               <p>As to Stapleton his words are nothing to the purpoſe, ſeing he ſpeakes only of conciliar Definitions in matter of Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. 6. Whatſoeuer the Holy Father the Pope doth, if it be Theft, or any other thing, which of it ſelf is euil (as for example MUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER, &amp;c.) we muſt like wiſe impute that to the jnſpiration of GODS ſpirit.</q> And you cite C. <hi>non nos D.</hi> 40. <hi>in Gloſſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer: no greate wonder you <hi>Proteſtant Miniſters,</hi> ſhould falſify gloſſes of <hi>Canons,</hi> who build your Faith on falſifications of the ſcriptures. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther canon, nor Gloſſe ſay, what you produce them for, both lay the quite contrary. The title of the Canon is: <hi>The Papal office doth not giue; but takes a way the liberty to ſin.</hi> In the canon: <hi>we do not think, that God hath giuen vs any leaue to ſin.</hi> In the Gloſſe: <hi>when the Action is dubious whether it be good, or bad, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> muſt judge fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably of the Pope</hi> If it be of its <hi>own nature bad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as Adultery, or MVRTHER: we muſt own that he ſins in it: althô there be no man to whom he ought to be accuſed,</hi> by reaſon of the dignity of the firſt Chair.</p>
               <p>You ſee, ſir, that the gloſſe ſays iuſt the contrary to what you cite out of it: for it ſays the Pope ſins by <hi>murther;</hi> &amp; you make it ſay, <hi>murther</hi> is no ſin in a Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. 6. As yet we haue not proued vpon them
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37671:14"/>their KING KILLING doctrine pray let one quotation ſupply for all, &amp; I think it is ſuch an one, as is ſull home to the Point. <hi>Suarez</hi> l. 6. ad M. B. Regem 1.24 ſays. A King if he be once excommunicated, may be depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or ſlain by any perſon whomſoeuer: &amp; that with impunity. <hi>Therefor it is paſt all manner of doubt,</hi> but that they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld it exreamely Lawfull.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer: <hi>It is paſt all manner of doubt, that you hold it extreamely Lawfull</hi> to tell any kind of lyes, &amp; falſify any Authours you pleaſe, prouided it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contribute to charge ſome odious opinion on <hi>Papiſts,</hi> how contrary ſoeuer it be to the Authours you cite. <hi>Suarez</hi> hauing written that Propoſition immediatly addes: <hi>Haec Propoſitio ſimpliciter ſumpta eſt falſiſsima. This Propoſition abſolutely taken, is moſt falſe.</hi> What ſay you, Chriſtian Reader, is this fair play? what cannot theſe men proue at this rate out of any Authour; by making him ſay what he condemnes, &amp; condemn what he ſays? What credit do they deſerue, who diſcouer ſo little ſenſe of Truth, honeſty, ſhame of men, or feare of God?</p>
               <p>Theſe are his proofes of our holding <hi>Murther to be Lawfull,</hi> which he doth not 1. becauſe there is not one word cited out of any English Catholick.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor out of any other aliue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He falſitys impudently all he cites.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER 6. Catholicks practice no Treaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. 7. What was the offence of the Cittizens of <hi>Toulouſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Auignon,</hi> when P. Gregory IX. Set Lewis the French King to war againſt them, &amp; their Earl <hi>Raymundus,</hi> without cauſe, but only that of their Religion, &amp; where the ſayd King dyed at the ſiege?</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. Here are two greate vntruths.</p>
               <p>The firſt, that <hi>there was no cauſe of that war, beſides Religion.</hi> There were two wars made vpon the Albigenſes The firſt by <hi>Simon Monfort,</hi> with the forces of the King of <hi>France,</hi> Lewis VIII. Soveraign Lord of the Earle of <hi>Toulouſe,</hi> for hauing killed an Embaſſador, or Legat, againſt the law of nations. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond by Lewis himſelfe for their Herely, &amp; <hi>Rebellion.</hi> So neither war was on the ſcore of Religion purely.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:37671:14"/>
               <p>The ſecond vntruth is, that the King of France dyed at the ſiege. He finisht the war, vnited thoſe Countryes to the crowne, &amp; on his way home he dyed at <hi>Monpenſier</hi> in <hi>Auvergn.</hi> See <hi>De Serres</hi> a <hi>Huguenot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p. 7. You giue many inſtances of crueltys ſhewed towards <hi>Hereticks</hi> in <hi>Cabrieras Merindol, Prouenc, Vaſſy,</hi> Germany, the <hi>Lowcountryes,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To all I anſwer they were rebels, ſtood in open defiance of the Ancient Laws eſtablisht, &amp; of their Princes commands.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p. 7. Pray for the fuller ſatisfaction in this thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide D. Fowlis his Hiſtory of their <hi>Rebellions</hi> &amp; Treaſons, read <hi>the vngratefull be hauiour of the Papiſts &amp; Prieſts,</hi> towards the Imperial Indulgent crown of England.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw: I will not vndertake to vindicate the actions of all <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that haue been; I ſpeake for thoſe aliue. If any here to fore were really guilty of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> I excuſe them not yet the late proceedings againſt <hi>Catholicks,</hi> althô certainly <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,</hi> yet charged with the moſt heauy Accuſations imaginable, ground a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition that their Anceſtors may haue had hard meaſure in that kind. Howeuer if our fore fathers left any blot on their Religion by ſome illegall attempts, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks ſince haue washt it out with their Bloud. And I pray God with all my hart, that all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were as faith full to the Royal intereſt, as <hi>Papiſts</hi> are.</p>
               <p>In your pages 8. &amp; 9. I find nothing worth mentioning, but a ſaying of <hi>Aeneas Syluius,</hi> that nothing is giuen at <hi>Rome</hi> but for mony, not euen jmpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands, &amp; what you cite out of <hi>Caramuel: that a Prieſt may kill a Detractor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to <hi>Aeneas Syluius</hi> he recalled all thoſe writings being made Pope <hi>Pius</hi> II. This is ſo fals that <hi>Abſolution,</hi> which is <hi>one impoſition of hands,</hi> was neuer refuſed any man vpon ſcore of Pouerty. And as for <hi>Caramuel,</hi> that propoſition is condemned by <hi>Alexander</hi> VIII. <hi>Caramuel</hi> hath no credit euen in his own order (he is a <hi>Bernardin</hi>) his writings being forbidden amongſt them vnder great Penaltys.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p. 10. The Pope is called by <hi>Papiſts: our Lord God the Pope.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer: thoſe words are found but once, &amp; that in a <hi>Gloſſa:</hi> which ſort of writings are little regarded by our Divines. Howeuer you haue no reaſon to reproach vs with that expreſſion, who ſay the ſame of all <hi>Kings</hi> pag. 16. &amp; of all <hi>men,</hi> pag. 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p. 11. <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſays, God hath giuen to the Pope the Power to make ſin to be no ſin; &amp; no ſin to be ſin.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer, this imports no more, then that God gaue the Pope to oblige by his laws the conſcience of the Faithfull in things indifferent: viz, eating flesh on a wedneſday which of it ſelf is no ſin, but is a ſin when forbidden. But <hi>Bellarmin</hi> expreſſely ſays, that the Pope cannot make <hi>Lawfull</hi> a thing of it ſelf cuil, as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37671:15"/>
                  <hi>Theft,</hi> or <hi>Murther:</hi> nor <hi>vnlawfull</hi> a thing of it ſelf good, as the loue of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p. 11. What could ſtirr the Roman Catholicks vp to that dreadfull Rebellion &amp; maſſacre in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where in cold Blood were murdered aboue 100000. <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> without the leaſt prouocation, but only the <hi>Indiſpenſable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity</hi> to kill <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer. The late King knew other reaſons: Theſe are his words: <hi>The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous vigour, &amp; vnreaſonable ſeuerity, which ſome men carryed before them in England was not the leaſt incenture that kinaled, &amp; blew vp into thoſe horrid flames the deſpair of diſcontent which wanted not prediſpoſed fewel for Rebellion in</hi> Ireland: <hi>where Diſpayre being added to their former diſcontens, &amp; the Feares of vtter extirpation to their wonted oppreſsions, it was eaſy to prouoke to an open Rebellion, a People prone enough to breake out to all exorbitant violence, both by ſome Principles of their Religion, &amp; the natural deſire of Liberty: both to exempt themſelues from their preſent reſtraints, &amp; to preuent thoſe after rigours where with they ſaw themſelues apparently threatned by the Couetous zeale, &amp; vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>haritable fury of ſome men, who think it a greate argument of the Truth of their Religion, to endure no other, but their own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Rebells were exaſperated to the moſt deſperate Reſolutions, &amp; Actions, by being threatned with all extremitys, not only, to the knowne heads, &amp; cheiſe Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diarys; but euen to the whole community of the Nation; reſoluing to deſtroy Root &amp; Branch, men, women, &amp; children: without any regard to thoſe vſual pleas for mercy, which Conquerors not wholy barbarous, are wont to hear from their own breaſts, in behalfe of thoſe, whoſe oppreſtiue faces, rather then their malice engaged them, or whoſe imbecillity for ſex, or age was ſuch, as they could neither lift vp a band againſt them.</hi> Thus his late Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Here you ſee, Sir, not a little; but a great, &amp; manifold <hi>cauſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Prouocation</hi> to that <hi>Rebellion,</hi> (which I do not intend to juſtify) viz.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Deſire of Liberty in a nation ſubject to a foreigner.</item>
                  <item>2. Wonted oppreſſions,</item>
                  <item>3. Diſcontents grounded on them.</item>
                  <item>4. Deſpayre being threatned with <hi>vtter extirpation, Roote &amp; Branch, man, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp; Child.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>When you haue conſidered this you will conclude that very little of that <hi>Rebellion</hi> can be charged on <hi>Religion.</hi> So your ſaying <hi>it was without the leaſt cauſe, or Pronocation,</hi> is Rash, falſe, &amp; vn charitable.</p>
               <p>Moreouer the readineſs with which the <hi>Irish</hi> accepted a <hi>Ceſſation of Armes,</hi> when offred by his Majeſty, (as you may ſee in that place) althô without that ceſſation the <hi>Proteſtant Party</hi> had perisht, shews the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſought <hi>ſelf Preſervation,</hi> as the King ſays; not <hi>deſtruction of Hereticks,</hi> as you faſly ſurmiſe.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37671:15"/>
               <p>All which I ſay, not to excuſe al the <hi>Irish</hi> Actions; but to diſcouer your want of truth and charity in charging all on <hi>Religion,</hi> which is Innocent, euen when thoſe, who profeſſe it, offend, becauſe ſhee teaches not, nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proues thoſe offences.</p>
               <p>Pag. 11. &amp; 12. You relate ſome words &amp; actions of ſome Popes; which I think Religion not concerned in, ſeing it doth not oblige vs to think them impeccable in words, or Actions. What if a teſty Pope ſayd <hi>either he would haue Philip's Crowne, or Philip should haue his Miter:</hi> it was a Paſſionate expreſſion. And if <hi>S. Gregory</hi> congratulated <hi>Phocas</hi> his being Emperour, &amp; commended his <hi>Mercifull Acts,</hi> it may as well betaken for an exhortation to <hi>mercy;</hi> as relation of what he was.</p>
               <p>Pag. 13. You charge Religion with the maſſacre of <hi>Paris;</hi> althô done without the Pope's knowledge, &amp; reſolued on by the King, to rid his kindome of thoſe who had lately endangered his Crowne. It was a pain of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> not of <hi>Hereſy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pag. 14. You cite ſtrange things out of <hi>Fraſuis du veron. Bonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, white &amp; Mariana.</hi> Who hauing all been condemned by <hi>Catholicks</hi> none aliue reading them, as far as I know, <hi>Catholicks</hi> cannot with any colour of Iuſtice be charged with their writings. If you pleaſe to look backe to 42. you will heare all Pulpits ringing with, and Prints ſpeaking of as deſperate things, as in any of of thoſe writers, as far as I know of them.</p>
               <p>Pag. 15. You ſerue vp againe your cold cabbadge the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> &amp; the war on the <hi>Albigenſes.</hi> To which I haue already anſwerd.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p. 15. With what pompous ceremonys do they hallow thoſe Inſtruments, which are to do the bleſſed worke? By what charming names do they call that Bloudy wretch, who is to be employed in the Horrible Buſineſs? No leſſe then <hi>Elected ſon of God, Bleſſed veſsel, the Arme of the Almyghty to execute his Iuſtice.</hi> How they blaſphemouſly come before their Altars, &amp; with a ſeeming feruent zeale, pray to the God of Heauen, <hi>That all the Saints may ariſe, &amp; giue place vnto him: &amp; that the Lod may appeare to be his ſtrength, &amp; to in fuſe, into him the Beames of his Conſolation!</hi> How do they Diuilishly whe edle him into a beleife, that there is a celeſtial ſplendour shining round his head, &amp; like the skin of <hi>Moſes</hi> his face, appearing with ſo greate abryghtneſs, that they are not capable of looking on him without Trembling, &amp; Confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How do they throw themſelues proſtrate at his Feete, &amp; pretend that he is no more a mortal; but changed into a Deity? And how they tell the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Cully, that he will by ſo glorious an Action be certainly freed from the paines of Purgatory, &amp; immediatly tranſlated into Paradiſe, &amp; there be ſwallowed vp of Eternall Delights, &amp; ſatisfactions?</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37671:16"/>
               <p>I haue giuen this place at large, that you may ſee the Malice, &amp; Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of it. In what place did this happen? what man euerſaw it? what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour euer mentioned it? The <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> in his Annotations on the ſpeechs of the fiue <hi>Ieſuites</hi> was the firſt, that euer mentioned it, as far I could euer diſcouer: till he name another, I shall take him to be the Authour of this Fable. Yet it hath loſt nothing in your hands. <hi>The ſplendour</hi> of his face like that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Papiſts falling at his Feet,</hi> are of your inuention. And who can tell what further Additions may be made by others: For in theſe jmaginary ſpaces of Fictions, who can ſix any bounds to <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who without ſcruple tell any lye, as a Truth? But the ſucceſſe is quite other then you pretend: for thus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in vaine to proue vs guilty; you effectually proue vs Innocent. I aſſure you, that when any of our Church shall write againſt you, he will find Truth enough to ſay, without hauing recourſe to ſuch lyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p 17. They hold it to be no ſin <hi>Not to keepe Faith, nor Peace, not to obſerne either Truth or Honeſty towards Hereticks: it is no deceite to Equiuocate with them in priuate Dealings, or Publick Tranſactions; 'tis no Dishoneſty to cheate them of what they haue, no Periury to breake Oaths with them, no Toeſ to rob or ſpoile them, 'tis no inhumanity to burn their Houſes ouer their heads, no Murther to kill them, altho KINGS, and PRINCES: in a word, tis no ſin for all Relations, to deny them what God hath made their Reſpectiue Dutys.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. We diſown this Doctrine in all its parts: &amp; our liues confute it ſufficiently, but yours is ſo conformable to it, that we may think it a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your owne practice. Adde only th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hiring men of deſperate fortunes &amp; flagitious liues, to beare falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> witneſſe againſt Innocent Papiſts, with vaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, applauding their Depo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gh euidently falſe, &amp; accompanyed with that infallible ſigne of a lye, contradictions, condemning honeſt &amp; loyal ſubjects vpon ſuch mocke euidence to the greateſt Penaltys which the law ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points for real Traitors &amp;c. and we haue a perfect picture of your proceedings with <hi>Papiſts. Stupor &amp; mirabilia facta ſunt in terrà, Prophetae prophetabant mendacium: &amp; Sacerdotes applaudebant manibus ſuis: &amp; populus meus dilexit talia: quid ergo fiet in nouiſsimis eius?</hi> Hierem 5.30.31. <hi>A wonderfull &amp; horrible thing is committed in the Land,</hi> England: <hi>the Prophetes</hi> (<hi>Oates</hi> &amp; <hi>Dugdale</hi>) <hi>Prophecy falſly, &amp; the Preiſts (Miniſters) applaude this with their hands, &amp; my People,</hi> vpon whom I haue ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo many Bleſſings, <hi>Loue all this: what will become of them in the end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. Jf <hi>Murthering</hi> of <hi>Hereticks</hi> ſhould really be a ſin (as none of them will acknowledge) yet ſo long as the <hi>Preiſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieſuites</hi> shall tell them to the contrary, nay ſhall cry it vp for a ſignal Act of Piety, they are bound to beleiue them, &amp; ſo many MURTHERS as People shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37671:16"/>on ſuch a beleif, &amp; from the pure Principle of blind obedience, ſo many worthy, &amp; Holy Actions do they perform, &amp; by a neceſſity of conſequence do merit accordingly. Therefore how greate muſt needs be their Reward in Heauen, who shall not only haue their hands imbrued in a few trifling, petty <hi>Murthers,</hi> but ſhall make whole nations ſwim in Blood, &amp; shall not ſpare their Magiſtrates Princes, or Kings.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. Here is not one true word: &amp; the whole diſcourſe relyes on two abominable lyes, equall to thoſe of <hi>Oates,</hi> your <hi>Brother Miniſter.</hi> The firſt that <hi>none of us will acknowledge MVRTHER of Hereticks to be a ſin.</hi> We vnanimouſly profeſſe it is a ſin: we are ready to ſigne it with our Blood, if need be. We declare, we beleiue that it is a mortal ſin for any priuate man to kill another, vnleſſe it be for his owne neceſſary defence. This we ſay, &amp; are ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme with Oath.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Lye, is, <hi>that Papiſts are bound to beleiue what their Preiſts teach, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the law of God, &amp; that MVRTHER committed in conſequence of that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe becomes meritorious.</hi> This is moſt falſe, all <hi>Papiſts</hi> know they muſt obey God rather then men &amp; the credit they giue to their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> is meerly becauſe they teach what God commands. And did they find their <hi>Preiſts</hi> guilty of ſuch lyes, as you of the Miniſtry fill your Sermons, &amp; Libellous writing with, (contrary to the law of God: <hi>thou shalt not beare falſe witneſſe</hi>) they would neuer vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to heare them, but caſt them off, as a pack of knaues.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. pag. 21. I think this will ſuffice, to make clear the Truth of my whole Aſſertion, how the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> account MURTHER &amp; TREASONS to be <hi>Lawfull, neceſsary, commendable, &amp; meritorious.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer. You haue proued no one of all thoſe points: we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt them all: we proteſt, we hold MURTHER &amp; TREASON vnlawfull on all occaſions: &amp; that neither the one nor the other can be <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</hi> When ſoeuer his ſacred Majeſty shall be pleaſed to order it, all the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> &amp; other <hi>Preiſts</hi> in his Dominions are ready to declare in ſuch forme as he ſhall preſcribe them, that they deteſt MURTHER &amp; TREASON, &amp; all Doctrine teaching either of them: &amp; all this in the obuious plaine ſenſe of the words, without <hi>AEquiuocation,</hi> or <hi>mental Reſeruation,</hi> which two ways of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aking a man's mind they renounce, &amp; acknowledge to haue been deſeruedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. 2. Mar. 1679.</p>
               <p>And they do further declare, that they ſhall think themſelues ſenſibly obliged to any Perſon, who shall procure his Majeſties conſent to the making of ſuch a publick Declaration.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p. 21. I shall now come to giue the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37671:17"/>CONSIDERATIONS vpon what I haue ſayd, &amp; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. Thoſe who deſign miſchiefe to a town giue fals allar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, that defendants being drawn to a place where there is no danger, may neglect thoſe where there is ſome. Whether you intend ſuch a ſtratagem, I cannot tell; but I am ſure your <hi>conſiderations</hi> are needleſſe to Peaceable Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and neceſſary to your <hi>ſeditious Brethren.</hi> So you mis apply your Plaſter, where there is no ſore.</p>
               <p>I will not gratify ſo much the Factious party, as to examin your <hi>Conſiderations.:</hi> &amp; shew their defects. Whereof ſome are childish: ſome others ſubſtantiall in themſelues, &amp; taken out of Popish Authours, yet handled ſo awk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, that I once thought you Preuaricated &amp; would diuert your Readers from their Duty to their Prince, by commending it weakly. Yet I hope this proceedes from an inability to compoſe ſtronger diſcourſe. Indeed thoſe ſtrong Reaſons taken out of <hi>Papiſts</hi> in your vnderſtanding, are not vnlike to <hi>Hercules's</hi> club in the hand of a Pigmey.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">E. C. p. 30. For our King, let all true loyall harts pray with me.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer. J I pray God, that both you, &amp; all the Miniſtry did hartily pray for his Majeſty. I do aſſure you, that <hi>Papiſts,</hi> &amp; particularly <hi>Ieſuites</hi> doe pray hartily for him: &amp; I will confirme it out of a Pamplet printed in french by a <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> in which ſpeaking to the fiue executed, he ſays: <hi>Pray alſo for his Majeſty: that God be pleaſed to giue him a wiſe Council, faithfull officers, couragious armys, a Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable People, a happy raigne, a long life, &amp; an eternal Glory.</hi> This I aſſure you that <hi>Ieſuit</hi> ſayd from his hart: &amp; is ready to ſeale it with his blood.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
